We wanted to use this logo
against Richard Hartley 's piano playing of the Twentieth Century Fox theme .
We wanted to use that
for the denouement instead of the RKO sign .
That was interesting . Lou Adler and Michael White , our producers .
- Yes , that 's correct . - Erstwhile people .
I 'm rather missing ...
Whose mouth do you think this might be ?
- Mine ! - Yeah , it is .
Interesting enough , when we did the stage play
it was you that sang this song .
They offered you the part of Magenta in the movie , and what did you say ?
They told me I wasn 't going to be able to sing the song .
They couldn 't have an usherette open the film .
So I 'd lost my song , " Science Fiction . "
And I said , " You can take your movie and shove it up your ... "
Where the sun don 't shine ?
They were very amazed , because they had taken me to a restaurant .
Always do it after lunch . Always tell them no after lunch .
" No , " after lunch . And I said , " I 'm not interested , I won 't do it . "
Then they took me to John Goldstone
the other producer , to his house to see the set .
He said , " Please , Pat , come and see , come and just have a look . "
Then they showed me the pink room , the laboratory
and then all the drawings of the costumes and whatever , whatever .
And I said , " I can 't wait . I 'll begin tomorrow . "
I didn 't mind about the song .
Yeah , I didn 't know anything about that until this moment in time .
I 've blamed you for it ever since .
I got along to the studio and they 'd done the backing tracks .
The crew had done the backing tracks at Olympic Studios , and they said ...
I love my name dripping like that .
- Sorry . - It was a bit of a trip .
They said , " I want you to sing the opening title song
because you 're the author of this show . "
I said , " What do you mean , as a guide vocal for Pat ? "
They went , " No , we want you to sing it . " And so I did .
Until that moment in time , I had no idea that ...
Ladies and gentlemen , or whoever 's listening .
Today is the first time this has been revealed in how many years ?
- I think 25 years . - In all these years
I have begrudged you taking my song .
And all these years I 've begrudged you
for having that delightful mouth .
- Thank you . - I mean , look , it 's a wonderful mouth .
One wonders , you know . Well , wonders , just wonders , really .
Has your dentist seen this movie ?
Yes , I want to give her a plug . Veronica Morris .
Because she 's been keeping my teeth in great order .
This is marvelous .
Veronica will be so pleased .
This mouth , of course , is Brian Thomson 's idea .
It was the Man Ray photograph of the mouth in the sky .
Was it a photograph ? I thought it was a painting .
- It 's a photograph . - It 's a photo , Lips Over Hollywood .
Is that what it is ?
It 's over the Hollywood sign , a mouth .
- Man Ray . - And this was the first mouth .
I 'd never seen a mouth ...
The Rolling Stones got a mouth after that didn 't they ?
They got a mouth after . Not a mouth before .
- A bit mouthy . - A bit mouthy .
It was wonderful when they asked me to do this
because they asked me to do this on the very last day of the film .
Jim Sharman came up to me , " It 's a wrap . Finished . "
He came up and said , " We 've got an idea about this mouth .
Will you do it ? "
They painted all your skin black .
Yes , and I went out to the L Street Studios .
Your timing is perfect . Your lip-synch is fantastic .
Yes , well , I 'm good at that .
And I sort of know how you do things .
Ramon Gow , look , the hairdresser .
- We 'll talk about Ramon . - Yes , he 's wonderful .
He kept us happy .
And Pierre La Roche . Pierre did the makeup , didn 't he ?
Pierre La Roche , oh , God . He did Bowie 's makeup
for what was that Bowie thing ?
You know , when he had the makeup .
When did Bowie never have makeup ?
- All right , well Bowie ... - Ziggy Stardust .
Yes , it was fantastic .
I thought , " Guy La Roche will give me the most fantastic face . "
And he looked at me and gave me no bones , no nothing .
- Pierre La Roche . - Pierre , right .
I beg your pardon , Pierre La Roche .
I was so shocked that he just said :
" Right , we 're going to totally whiten the face . " And what ?
- Here we are . - We fade into the cross there .
Fade into the cross , yeah .
And down the old ...
Now , this is interesting , because this was just a façade .
There 's a little room on stilts behind that door , a tiny little room .
There 's darling Henry Woolf . He 's such a darling friend .
Perry Bedden 's in the front here .
Perry was the boyfriend of Brian Thomson at the time .
That little girl there , where is she ?
She was the photographer , went out with Prince Andrew .
- Koo Stark . - Koo Stark , yeah , she 's in the back .
She 's there .
I was going to point to the screen but that doesn 't make a difference .
- Gaye Brown , there 's Pierre . - And Henry .
Henry was in my house the other evening . He teaches in Saskatchewan .
He 's doing a Harold Pinter play .
That 's right . He was in the first play that Pinter wrote .
He made him write it , actually .
- Well , there they are . - There 's our Brad .
Ouch , that hurt .
There she is , Susan Sarandon .
We didn 't know these people when they arrived , just their background .
He had been doing Grease on Broadway .
Great dancer , great legs . It was wonderful .
There 's my wife jumping up and down , my ex-wife .
Is it ? Kimi ?
- In that little plaid . - And her lovely handbag .
- With the bangs . - Yes .
Gorgeous .
This is Rufus Thomas , I think , driving the car .
There he is . He was with the Living Theater for some years .
He came over and choreographed Jesus Christ Superstar
in its first British incarnation .
Gosh .
- Such class we had in this . - We were all very groovy .
I don 't remember those two .
There 's us in the background being American Gothic .
It was freezing cold that day .
I 'll never talk about the cold again on this film .
I remember walking to that set the first day
we 'd smoked something rather exotic .
- I 'd never smoked before . - No .
Richard led me into really bad ways .
- It was difficult clinging to reality . - It was wonderful .
I loved it .
- There we go . - There 's our signs .
- In the graveyard . - Denton .
Home of happiness .
" Damn it , Janet . "
She looked pretty . Sue Blane did wonderful costumes .
They 've really hung on .
Even though we do the stage show 20 ...
Well , it 's longer than 25 years for the stage show
but we still use Sue 's design .
She reinvents them and it 's still the same kind of look .
I must say she 's stunning . At the time
I demand that Sue Blane invented punk and this film invented punk .
Down the road was Vivian Westwood with a shop called Sex .
She thought she started it .
No , she copied us from up the road . We were on-stage at the time .
There 's a certain truth in that .
I think we were a precursor of Malcolm McClaren and Vivian .
But then again you see , Coco Chanel said :
" Those who think they 're original have no sense of history . "
Look at that heart there . I want you to see that .
When we go back and rub it out , I think it 's the same heart .
I thought it was a different one .
There 's a boom microphone shadow that we 'll see soon .
- Why are you pointing out the faults ? - Why not ?
That 's what the fans do .
- Do they ? - Yeah .
Look , she dropped it . What a shame .
Wasn 't she meant to ? Obviously not .
Now this is interesting . This room , we could only afford this end
and the other end .
We didn 't have any sides to that room , so we could only shoot
looking this way or the other way .
We couldn 't pan around because there were no sides to this room .
Not enough money .
So there we go , you see , walking towards camera without background .
Good heavens .
And walking away from camera to there , but there were no sides .
They were very good .
When you consider we 'd ...
We were like a family , and they came in
and they joined in so easily , so quickly .
I find them astonishing .
I don 't want to go into detail , but it 's a very small coffin , isn 't it ?
- One does wonder . - Wonder what ?
You know , there could have been a rabbit in there probably .
Every day was a surprise to me on Rocky Horror .
I never knew what was going to happen next .
I didn 't know what American Gothic was
till I saw the painting on the hall a few days later .
I thought , " Why am I dressed like this ? "
- You 're not familiar with it ? - No !
There we are , three good-looking people .
Those opticals worked rather good .
They really were mechanically derived by ...
But today , of course , you have optical wipes
and all sorts of things with video .
There 's dear Charles Gray , who 's departed from us recently .
- Yes , Charlie . - And I loved it when you said to me
it would be wonderful if we were Charles Gray and Ava Gardner .
We could visit each other .
They were great friends . They lived next door to each other .
They 've both gone , so we 've got to now move into the same street .
They 're probably in a similar street in the sky somewhere
doing the same things .
And Sinatra phoning every day .
- Yeah , did Sinatra ... ? - Phone Ava every day .
- Oh , did he ? - Yeah .
There 's the lovely Jonathan Adams ...
- ... who was our original narrator . - Brilliant .
He plays Dr. Scott in the movie .
And Brian Thomson used to put in hidden detail
so there would be stuff inside that file .
There might have even been stuff in those files behind him .
That was relative but nobody was ever going to see .
Well , to me , Brian Thomson 's set was astonishing . It was unbelievable .
I 've just been to see The King And I and the set that he did for that .
- I adored it . - It 's good , is it ?
- Pity about the person . - Sumptuous . No , no .
- I didn 't say anything . - No , nothing .
- Never heard of dickey bird there . - Yeah .
Charming person . Will be remembered in my will , actually .
Look at this nice car there , that Woody .
What was the tape playing , was it Nixon ?
Nixon 's ... I don 't like that speech being played , actually .
It locks the movie into a time frame .
I thought it was clever .
And so that late November evening wasn 't in time
with Nixon 's speech .
And , you know , there 's lots of things .
See the motorcyclists ?
Those people who played Transylvanians were on those motorbikes .
They were to go to the studio this very night
dress up , put all their Transylvanian gear on
and then put motorbike leathers on as well .
- Then go out on motorbikes to ... - They didn 't drive them themselves .
No , they had motorcyclists .
They paid pinion passengers . And as Ramon Gow said , you know ...
I said , " Why are they doing this ? It could be anybody in the dark . "
He said , " Could be a gorilla with a pipe , love . Gorilla with a pipe . "
I 'll never forget seeing the Transylvanians .
They were rehearsing in a room in the house .
We didn 't have Transylvanians in the play . Suddenly this door was open ...
And I don 't want to sound politically non-correct
but it was so freaky because they were freaks .
- Sorry . - As indeed we all are .
- No , speak for yourself . - It 's true .
In the amazement of tall , small , fat , thin , you know .
You lost the sense of norm , sense of center ?
Yes , and I saw all these people doing the " Time Warp . "
And I almost collapsed , I couldn 't believe it .
I didn 't know they were going to be in this .
I didn 't know there was a cast of Transylvanians .
When I went into the room and David Toguri was rehearsing them
and Barry Bostwick and Susan Sarandon was standing
amongst these people
with hugely different physiques . Physically so varied .
I 'll never work again for saying , " freak . "
It seemed to me that Susan and Barry
who most people would say are good-looking human beings
seemed just as freakish .
- The standard had disappeared . - Yes , right .
And that was interesting .
When we did the show , this line , " Over at the Frankenstein place "
made me relax , because my sphincter was tight .
The sweat on my brow was thick .
- My heart was pumping . - Was it ?
Because I was behind the screens , wondering if anyone would like it
or were they gonna go sit there going ...
Oh , dear Richard !
And we all sang that line :
" Over at the Frankenstein place , there 's a light , " and they laughed .
The minute they laughed I went , " Oh , it 's all right . "
Everything will be all right .
If they 're laughing at that , they 'll laugh at the rest .
- It 'll all be okay . - Oh , God .
Now this is where , of course , Susan began to get the flu .
We 'd been shooting and late ...
Please don 't talk about her damn flu anymore .
That 's all she ever discusses , much as I love her .
- Excuse me . - Sorry .
Here we are , gorilla with a pipe , you see . There 's all Transylvanians .
All in , with their tailcoats underneath all that , and why ?
- Who 's that beauty in the window ? - This is my favorite bit .
It was very dangerous going up there .
- There was no floor . - Floors are all gone .
This house was owned by someone who lived in France .
- It was the only reason ... - They 'd taken lead off the ceiling .
... they put money into it . Now it 's a hotel which is a bit of a shame .
And they built buildings around it .
Yeah , but they have Rocky Horror weddings and honeymoons .
It is the top window . I thought it was the second window .
Okay . I thought it was a completely different window .
- We 've gone quiet . - We have really .
It was so Gothic and so wonderful , the lightning strike in there .
It 's a good-looking movie .
Jim Sharman 's first major film as a director .
He pulled this together well .
Who was our lighting cameraman ? Suschitzky ?
Peter Suschitzky , the prince of darkness .
I loved you for that . I remember we weren 't allowed to see the rushes .
I don 't know if you ever knew that .
I didn 't want to see them . If you 're acting , you shouldn 't .
Rubbish ! I have to see them .
And Little Nell and I used to sneak in and see them all the time .
We did see the prince of darkness ' work .
Yeah , it 's good , isn 't it ? He 's a good man .
And he 's Woolf 's son .
This house , of course , has been used in many , many films .
The Innocence . You probably remember it with Debra Carr and Peter Windgold .
- We talked about him earlier on . - Same house .
Oh , right . Well , it 's the Hammer ...
Hammer Studios . It was a cheap and easy location .
Just across the paddock .
That 's another thing
you with your wonderful English accent or your " Hello . "
Then I came from Transylvania , so I had a German accent .
Tim Curry had a Charring Cross Road , Kensington accent .
- Knightsbridge . - Knightsbridge .
And Nellie had her Australian .
And it was so peculiar because nobody ever , ever discussed
where they came from .
It made no difference .
Nobody 's asked any questions about it .
We had , of course , the ... Also another thing
that was very useful for the Americans , Barry and Susan .
We had that week and a half , two weeks at rehearsing
on a taped floor in an old abandoned hotel in Earl 's Court .
The White House Hotel .
I 'll never forget that day Meat Loaf walked in .
I 'd never met Meat Loaf before and I thought , " Who 's that ? "
And then he was strutting his stuff , I mean , very Texan .
- How the hell are you ? - How the hell are you , hon ?
And suddenly that voice sang " Hot Patootie "
and I swear there was a chandelier in the room and it did crash .
It 's amazing how we didn 't see you , yet we can see you now .
It 's amazing how we don 't see you until we see you .
That 's because the director didn 't tell me what to bloody do .
It was ridiculous and I didn 't dare upstage that moment .
You were very good .
No , to me that 's very bad .
No , I thought that was marvelous . A very theatrical moment .
That clock is an interesting thing .
That is a real skeleton
of the husband of the woman who had the clock made .
- No ! - It was a beautifully made ...
Is that where I should have put Robert ?
- You could have . - In the clock ?
You could 've done that .
There .
What a naughty pair .
Yes , well this is where the reception area is in the hotel .
It 's all very , very down market .
Not very nice at all . But it is , it 's all right .
That 's when that boy takes off .
There we are . That 's the sign . We were talking about that today .
When we were rehearsing we had to find a sign
that made us different . That we had something between us .
That 's kind of a handshake or ...
Our Transylvanian sign .
Go forth and prosper or whatever .
That was our alien sign .
There 's my wife in the middle , ex-wife , I should say , Kimi .
Yes , with her wonderful hair .
Mother of my child .
- Beautiful lioness . - Lucky boy .
There were all these actors .
- There 's Christopher Biggins . - Eating as usual .
- No , eating a doughnut , I think it was . - Eating the donut .
Stuffing the cream down his face .
I won 't go down that road with you .
- Which road ? - Your hair looks fabulous .
Ramon Gow , the wonderful hairdresser who was so lazy .
All he did was spray a can of red stuff on me every day .
We didn 't even dye it . I had black hair .
He sprayed it red with this terrible stuff every day .
Ramon is no longer with us . A lovely man .
I liked Ramon . He 'd work with everybody .
And nothing can ever be the same
You 're spaced out on sensation
Like you 're under sedation
Let 's do the time warp again
I was walking down the street Just having a think
When a snake of a guy Gave me an evil wink
He shook-a me up He took me by surprise
He had a pickup truck And the devil 's eyes
- There 's Little Nell . - Little Nellie .
Her father was a famous Australian journalist who talked about family
and used to write in the Australian newspaper .
Used to refer to Nell as Little Nell . That 's how she got that nomenclature .
Oh , I see .
Jim Sharman found her on the streets of London .
She used to , how do you put it , busk .
She was doing a bit of busking , of housekeeping .
She did a bit of housekeeping .
I love this , there we go .
She was cleaning for Jim
when we were casting for the stage production .
In rehearsal she used to say , " Nell 's the name , tapping 's the game . "
- There she goes . - There she goes .
I love this bit because Magenta gets very pissed off with her here .
She 's a recent mother .
She said on a recent interview , " Motherhood is wonderful .
I love being a mother . "
I love it , her talking about being a mother now .
I was a mother then . I had the baby in the bath .
Yeah , but poor old Nellie had been in a terrible car accident
about 10 or 15 years ago .
Was walking around for several weeks , getting these blinding headaches .
They took her to the hospital and discovered her neck was broken .
She 'd been walking around for weeks with a broken neck .
- I feel as if mine 's broken now . - She is a great survivor .
This was Fran Fullenwider who is no longer with us .
She 's in heaven too .
She wrote me a wonderful letter when my husband died .
- Well , recently ? - Recently .
Yeah , I 'm sorry about that , Fran .
She was in trouble one day and Jim Sharman was very cross and crotchety .
Well , he had to get the film done .
- How long did it take to make ? - Six weeks .
I stopped the show .
I remember your dear wife saying to me :
" I stopped the show because Fran had a coughing fit
and couldn 't go on , " and he got very cross with her .
So I sort of called a strike .
I didn 't remember that , but it 's been reminded .
- I 'm proud of that . - You were very ballsy in those days .
Fair .
I was fair .
- I thought you were a Reb ? - Honorable .
- There 's the beauty . - There he is . Mr. Curry .
When we were casting this originally
we had a young man , Jonathan Kramer , American .
Who 's also in heaven .
Who isn 't in heaven ? We 're lucky to be here .
Maybe we 'd be luckier to be up there .
And Jonathan was gonna do this part
and Tim came along
to audition for us .
I 'm afraid poor old Jonathan
never had a chance against this guy .
I heard Tim came in and said , " Let 's rip it up . " Did he say that ?
I heard that .
- But I knew Tim before this . - Me too .
Because I was working at the Royal Court Theatre .
I was playing much bigger parts than him .
He was rather in awe of me , I believe .
I 'm sorry , but he did . He was very kind and admiring .
Well , I knew him in Hair because we were in it together .
I always thought he was the most beautiful thing on stage .
When Jim and I were talking about putting the show on at the Royal
I looked for musclemen . I thought that 'd be a nice thing to do .
Go around to gyms and see if I could find a muscleman to play Rocky .
What a lovely way to spend your day .
And I went into a little gym in one of those streets . George Street .
Or Blanford Street off ...
- Who was there ? - Hang on .
Hang on , Baker Street , Blanford Street , George Street .
I went into this gym and there was a very sweaty man .
Ugly and sweaty man who 'd been pumping iron .
There was this young man who was living next door
above a place called the Speed Queen .
- The laundrette . - This is a laundromat .
And I thought that 's very nice . He asked what I was doing .
- I told him . - Was he in the gym ?
No , he lived in the flat , the apartment above the Speed Queen .
So why did he speak to you ? Oh , because he knew you from Hair .
I 'd just been doing some casting and the next thing , he auditioned for us .
- Oh , God , another accident . - Well , kind of .
Yes , wonderful .
When I auditioned for you singing a Jessie Matthews song .
Yeah , " Over My Shoulder " days .
And told you not to play the piano because the music would put me off .
Which it surely would 've done , because I can 't play the piano .
I said to Richard Hartley .
- He didn 't shave under his arms . - What you mean ?
He didn 't shave under his arms .
- Him and Julia Roberts . - He 's a real hussy .
A right little hussy .
Well , he 's a boy .
I know lots of boys that shave under their arms .
There 's that darling , little , small person . Little one .
You 're not allowed to say those words .
Oh , no , P.C. , okay .
Little one person .
Brad !
We 'll play along for now and pull out the aces when the time is right .
Slowly , slowly . It 's too nice a job to rush .
Hi , my name is Brad Majors and this is my fiancée , Janet Weiss .
You are ... ?
You are very lucky to be invited up to Frank 's laboratory .
I was always undressing people .
All I did was take bandages off people , undressing them .
- I was so fed up . - That 's what you were employed for .
A bloody domestic .
It was such hard work .
Now this was ginger ale , as far as I remember .
I know , I loved this . That 's what shocked me .
Everything shocked me . I never knew that was going to happen .
When did the lift get stuck ?
Now that only goes up to the first level .
It 's on a hydraulic .
It doesn 't actually go any further than just past the floor .
The floors are " accidenty " types .
This was a minstrel gallery which I believe is gone now .
And there was a lovely , beautiful glazed roof above that .
Now , we 're coming up out of the floor of another shot .
- There we go . - Clever .
Quite . This was in a pit . This is where the swimming pool was .
See , that elevator goes down into a hole .
That hole was a part of a tank
which is later used for the swimming pool .
I wasn 't around for pool days .
Well , we had to shoot all this
and get all this in the can so we could tear the set down .
And then build the swimming pool set .
- In the same spot . - I don 't know .
Surrounded by geniuses .
Magenta .
Columbia .
Go and assist Riff Raff .
I will entertain ...
Now he tells me to go and pull the cloths off the thingy .
I 've never worked so hard . I don 't do this work at home .
No .
Dear Tim , because he 'd played this on a lot of stages before he did it .
I just think his performance is fantastic . Terrific .
He also understood the camera , which was very nice .
None of us did . This was the first movie for us .
First major movie for all of us .
- He did understand the camera . - How ? It 's his first movie .
First movie for me . I 'd never done a movie before .
- Neither did he . - That 's what I 'm saying .
I see , he understood the camera . I thought you meant better than us .
- I think he did to some extent . - Excuse me , he was on it more .
Yeah , but he also understood the lens , how to play the lens somehow or other .
All I understood was how to lurk . Look at us lurking .
They gagged you in the back there . Thank God .
The only time she was quiet in six weeks .
I thought they were fetching , those masks .
There was something very surreal about those strange masks .
I don 't know where they came from .
They were just given to you and you were told to wear them ?
I just did everything I was told . I didn 't know what was happening .
It 's why you 've always been a favorite with me .
- I 'm not a stupid person . - No , of course you 're not .
- I can play Lady Macbeth , easily . - What 's the capital of France ?
What a fool .
The answer was there all the time .
It took a small accident to make it happen .
- An accident ! - Accident !
That 's how I discovered the secret .
That elusive ingredient .
That spark
that is the breath of life .
Yes .
I have that knowledge .
I hold the secret
to life itself !
Well , that 's what I felt , you see . For me the pink room went on forever .
I know it 's brilliant , but it went on .
Well , when you 're working in a small area ...
- ... it 's time-consuming . - Especially when it 's pink .
When you 're doing cover shots
and you 've got to do a different angle
a different POV , it becomes very time-consuming .
Very time-consuming .
I have photographs from the film of me on the floor , out of it , you know .
Just from hanging about .
Nobody ever knew what the hoopla was in the States .
- Hoopla . - Hoopla , Janet !
- Nobody knew what that meant . - I know .
- What does it mean ? - It 's , like , a circus term . Hoopla !
- With the whip . - I know ...
- ... but what does it actually mean ? - Hoopla .
It means attention , applause . Applause .
If you 're saying to the horse or something : " Hoopla ! "
- Regardez , regardez . - Regardez ? I don 't know .
When we did Shock Treatment , nobody understood .
- It 's like a cymbal crash in Variety . - That 'll do . Yes . No , it is not .
Sort of like the slapstick they used to use .
- It was an accent of ... - Hoopla !
Yeah , something of that nature .
Oh , Brad !
It 's all right , Janet .
This was wonderful too .
I watched this movie last night .
I 've seen it a few times , but I really appreciated it .
I remember this . This was torture
because it was the first time Tim undid the thingamajigs .
Jim Sharman was screaming , " Faster , go , do it more , do it more ! "
We didn 't have a second chance at it .
- It had to work , I think . - That 's right .
It did because they were going to put the colors into the water .
Although this is artificially induced , as you can see
those colors were going to stay in the water .
There was one take on this .
They were to be the colors of the rainbow .
They were supposed to be violet and indigo and red and green
and whatever those five colors ... That 's what it was supposed to be .
It 's interesting that we get a bandaged body , a skeleton .
Another bandaged body .
That 's okay .
Movie works .
Oh , how dramatic .
- It was . - Lovely Peter Hinwood .
Very charming man .
- Wonderful . He hadn 't acted before ... - Or since .
Or since ? And was a model . And he , for me
he 's so sympathetic and vulnerable .
And I think he 's wonderful in it .
I think he 's wonderful . Antique dealer now .
Of course , in those days you couldn 't get actors who had a build .
- Really ? They were all wasted . - Everyone 's pumping iron now .
I was amazed you could find a gym in those days .
In those days everybody wanted to look done in , you know
like they 'd been drinking with Peter O 'Toole
and your late husband Robert around the bar
for a long time because that was part of the gig , you know .
Francis Bacon and all of them . At the Salisbury , yes .
This was very difficult , wasn 't it ? Trying to time this .
Trying to get all this off in time .
- It wasn 't going to happen again . - It was very difficult .
I remember that day .
I choose to forget it .
I don 't remember carrying Tim like that . I don 't remember .
I remember the warmth around the back of my neck .
But I must say
you really did get kicked around in this , didn 't you ?
- You took a few knocks . - I did .
There 's Annabel Leventon ...
- ... from Hair . - Yeah .
And her director .
Pamela Obermeyer behind her . Christopher Biggins again .
Now that was a great little dance there .
I came up with that little dance step .
- Did you ? - In seconds .
I don 't know how . I 've never done it since .
I could have killed you . I could hardly do it .
And Toguri kept telling me I kept falling over .
It was that wiggling on one foot . I had high heels .
- We did it easily and quickly . - Did you make it up ?
In seconds .
- Because it 's not from the time warp . - Nope .
But did we just follow you ? Obviously .
Nell went , " Well , that looks good . "
I didn 't know where it came from because I 'm a terrible dancer
and we did it in seconds . And it was all over .
But it looked rather good , that little leg movement .
Yes . I love this bit . " He 's okay . "
When we did it in rehearsal , I gave Nellie a note for this .
She 'd hate the word " note , " and she goes , " He 's okay ! "
and changed it from how she 'd done it before .
And Tim Curry was so shocked that he really did react to it .
He was furious with her because she completely changed the tone of it .
And I loved it because it wasn 't what he was expecting .
So his fury was real .
I didn 't make him for you !
He carries the Charles Atlas seal of approval .
There 's Lindsay .
I went and did a Rocky Horror evening for her .
She 's the one with the big hair ?
Yes . An evening for her art center to raise some money .
I mean , all these ideas were wonderful . These props and presents
and it was glorious .
I find it wonderful just to watch it all happening .
Maybe I was watching this day 's filming , I 'm not sure .
I remember when the hobbyhorse comes it was a ...
- This moment is rather risqué . - Very naughty .
For the time . When is it ? 1973 ? That was ' 74 .
- The whole thing was a bit risqué . - I suppose it was . It must have been .
- Not that I ever thought so ... - " In olden days a glimpse of stocking . "
No , what shocked me was when they went to bed .
In the play , they didn 't actually go to bed .
- No . - No .
So when that happened , I thought , " Oh , dear .
I don 't know if I like this bit . "
- So I got a bit prudish then . - Oh , did you ?
Yes .
Because I thought we were in a nice
straight , clean show .
I didn 't know there was lots of hanky-panky going on .
When he pushes this horse , you know , this thing that he 's ...
I was brilliant at jumping that at school . I got prizes .
- Oh , really ? - Gymnastics .
- A plastic covered one like that ? - No , brown . Go on .
Watch while he pushes it away .
You 'll see it takes a little journey of its own .
- Oh , yes . - It was on some wires .
I never understood this .
Why nobody pushed that button , nobody opened it .
Of course , the double for Meat Loaf is nowhere .
He was smaller than me
and they padded him up .
- There. it was cut to Meat Loaf there . - Yeah .
But the double came off the thing .
He was fine , the motorcyclist and stuntman . He was fine .
- I know he was fine but he ... - He fell off ?
- The bike came off the ramp . - Did it ? I don 't remember that .
Oh , yes . And he wasn 't fine . He 's never been heard of since .
- I didn 't know that . - Yes .
It did . It came off .
I so loved it when we did the 15th convention at Fox Studios in Hollywood .
Meat Loaf sang " Hot Patootie , " and I dragged Nell out , broken neck or not .
I made her do the dance with him . And they did it perfectly .
It was lovely . They hadn 't forgotten it .
- Marvelous party . - Marvelous party .
Marvelous party .
- It 's nice there . - Isn 't Nell a card ?
I went to a wonderful party .
- But nobody asked me to play . - With Nunu and Nanu and Maude .
- With whom ? - I think it was Nunu , Nanu and Maude .
I couldn 't be sure about that .
Went to a marvelous party .
Why did they put a wig on him ?
I thought his own hair was equally effective .
- I forgot what his hair was like then . - He had long ponytail .
- Yeah , it was lovely . - Blond-y , mousy .
Yes , he was gorgeous .
There 's you and I grooving in the freezer .
- Back in the bloody freezer . - Yeah .
Keeping ourselves fresh .
While they 're having all the fun .
This was lovely . I loved this .
This was better than the Tiller Girls .
Now here we go . We 've got a swap from Meat Loaf
to double , stuntman .
A little tiny jump .
Now , Meat Loaf ... There we go . A different human being altogether .
Yes , that 's the one who went off the edge with that ...
Different human being .
Now , you 'll notice after the killing of Eddie
when Frank or Tim says , " He had no muscle . "
- Yeah . - And we had to shoot that again .
It was just after we 'd finished . We 'd wrapped but hadn 't gotten the shot .
It didn 't work , so we had to go back and we got some pink tiles
and they shot him against just these pink tiles .
- Goodness . - You 'll see in a minute .
You see ? I think it worked .
All this is while we were shooting .
Yeah .
Oh , that 's sweet .
There . That shot there was done after we 'd finished filming .
- Oh , I see . - I went back and got that little bit .
And put bits of the set together around behind him .
Yeah .
- But it cuts in quite nicely . - Yes , it works .
We 're looking as if we didn 't like him .
Well , but I didn 't . You see ? I didn 't .
Well , he was always beating the shit out of you .
I decided Riff didn 't like him very much
and was resentful for several reasons .
We were giving him his time .
Envy . Envy is a big one , of course .
- That 's a good one . - Yeah .
Good at playing that . What was mine ?
Because he was attractive and he got all the fans
and had all the witty lines .
And there was me , inarticulate and ugly with a hump .
I never thought of that .
Because I thought you were beautiful .
- It 's very nice of you to say . - Sorry .
I never saw you as that .
I guess that does rather say something about you there .
- Oh , Lord . Oh , dear . - I don 't remember pulling the curtain .
- Do you ? - Yeah .
- I don 't remember . - Standing there like toy soldiers .
- There 's Rufus Collins in the back . - Lovely man .
From the Living Theater .
It 's amazing how many of these people are no longer with us
since this filming .
After today , I assume two more might go .
- We 'll be there . - We 'll be there ?
We 're following along quite quickly .
What 's on that book ? One gets very interested then ...
- Yes , you do . You do . - ... in Brian Thomson 's stuff .
- Yes , in the hidden detail . - The wonderful eagle . Is it an eagle ?
What 's all this ?
Weird Fantasy , I think , is the title of that particular magazine .
Of course , all his stuff was shot in a day .
The marvelous thing is about the dining room scene
I read about in a magazine . I didn 't realize why
which we 'll see when we come to it .
I 'll talk about the set of the dining room scene .
Okay , I 'll bear that in mind . Just write that down .
Write that down . I 'll remember .
That what I think it is that you 've rolled up over there ?
I never liked the way you took so much pleasure in looking at that .
- What ? - In a voyeuristic sense .
Oh , do you see that ...
Making those noises . I got rather embarrassed .
- Oh , really ? - Yes .
See that thing around the TV screen ? I still have that .
- Where ? - In my shed . I 've got it in my shed .
- In your shed ? - It 's in my wee shed .
What do you do with it ?
It 's in the back of the house . The kids have shown and dressed in it .
- My son Linus would like it . - The one with all the pull handles ?
Just the square that goes around the TV screen and the handle on it .
It 's lost a couple of its rivets
as one does over the years .
This was the most brilliant idea . Wasn 't it ?
Well , absolutely . Because we needed no kind
of real close-ups of flesh or anything .
But where did it come from ? It came from the stage .
They didn 't have to take their clothes off .
But who invented this idea ?
It 's theatrical in its innocence and I think it
probably had to do with Jim Sharman 's prudery as well .
- But it worked . - Jim and me , the old prudes .
It works for us
because nobody is coerced into doing anything overt .
All the salaciousness disappears .
Yeah , it 's brilliant , and it just seems like happy fun time .
- Don 't you think ? - It 's divorced , somehow or another .
No clothes come off .
We know it 's very rude .
They gave me a bloody mop .
This is interesting . We saw that little scene
little look between the two of us in " Sweet Transvestite . "
Now again you see , subtext is ...
Darling , Lillian Gish has got nothing on me in silent movies .
This is the most silent movie I made . I 'm glad I 'm talking now .
And I had to do something , you know .
So I 've never made so many eyes or faces .
There are many directors that would be so locked into the main narrative ...
- ... the linear narrative ... - There wasn 't any .
... that they 'd get lost on the little subtext .
We might shoot them , but they 'd end up on the cutting-room floor .
- These little moments . - There isn 't a line spoken here .
This whole scene is silent . I 'm in a silent movie .
- We 're secondary players . - No , no .
We 're not here because the director has allowed us some breathing space .
But we would be secondary players in many films .
They 'd excise us from the whole thing . Then we wouldn 't be seen .
Then they would 've had no film .
All they would have had is the linear narrative text .
- Just the top line of ... - It would 've been a bit thin .
Yes , as it is with many films .
Look at this . This is our moment .
Well , it 's a moment , another moment . I wouldn 't say it 's our moment .
I never knew this was going on .
You know that I never thought I had anything to do with incest .
Then I thought , " What 's going on here ? " It 's our Dracula kiss .
I never had in my mind incest with my brother .
Because we made the sign together
and then the fans decided that it was an incestuous thing .
They call it an " elbow fuck . "
- Did they ? - Sorry . Yes .
- I 'm rather shocked . - Sorry , but that 's what they call it .
An elbow ... What 's another word for fuck ?
Do we need one ?
You said that people might have to be cut .
What can you do ... What do you do when you copulate ?
Copulate . An elbow copulation .
Thank you .
That 's what they all think we 're doing .
And I say , " No , we 're making our Transylvanian sign , you idiots ! "
When you bit my neck , they thought , " He 's up to no good . "
It 's the chemistry between us .
Well , I had none at all ! I was just doing my job .
And you were my brother , doing your work .
Doing his sister .
Not in my game , no .
I think that was always present in my mind as ...
It might have been in yours . It wasn 't in mine .
I think it works .
Because the innocence of you seems like indifference .
Cool indifference to the whole kind of idea , going :
" Oh , yes . Go on there , Riff Raff , if you want to .
Oh , dear . Are you all right now ? Are you happy now ?
Well , off you go . Toddle off . "
I wish I 'd known .
What 's happening here ? Where 's Brad ?
Where 's anybody ?
Oh , poor boy . Running through the rain , chased by Alsatians .
Magenta 's let loose the dogs .
Brad , my darling , how could I have done this to you ?
Now this song , here , was supposed to be intercut with ...
Not song . This action , this dialogue
was supposed to be intercut with Brad 's song .
- Oh , yes . - " Once in a While . "
" Once in a While , " which is wonderful .
- That cut , from there to there . - Yeah .
I think they work , cinematically , very well .
But Brad 's song was supposed to go between those cuts .
They were to cut in between the song . But the song was cut out of the piece .
Why , I 'm not quite sure .
I love Brad on the bed having a cigarette . I think it 's brilliant .
One of the things about the show
afterwards , was that it needed cuts .
But I think that was possibly because they didn 't understand it .
Fox , you know , green-lighted this movie .
They gave us the green light , the go-ahead .
And then they changed the head of Fox .
And Alan Ladd , Jr . , came in to be the head of Fox .
He didn 't want to do this movie . However , it was ...
That 's when he was with Gareth Wiggin , Georgia Brown 's husband .
... just too late for them to say no .
- Oh , good Lord ! - They turned up on the set .
Alan Ladd , Jr . , turned up and came down
when we were working out of Bray Studios .
He didn 't want this to happen , but it was too late .
By the time we finished the movie , he was no longer the head of Fox .
So it didn 't make any difference , because it was another person there .
- What a game of chance . - Then this was released .
They didn 't know who the target audience was .
Who was gonna go and see this movie ?
Tell us about it , Janet .
I loved Nellie painting my toes . Who thought that up ?
Maybe Jim Sharman directed that .
You two , probably .
Nellie and I sat in a very cold caravan
and talked about what we were going to do in our room .
And this idea , I think , is very sexy and very naughty .
I think it 's lovely , very intimate . Two kids playing together .
- That 's what it 's like ? - Yeah .
And her PJs were always so sweet .
Her pajamas ... She 's blowing my toes dry !
Yeah , but it 's not sexual . It 's that you 're two little chums .
- Yes . - You 're the same person , almost .
You were the same person .
You weren 't supposed to be two people when I wrote it .
- Oh . - You were the same person .
Oh , I see .
Jim Sharman said , " I 've got Marianne Faithfull . "
I know .
" She 's really interested in being in the show . "
And could we write a part for her ?
I said , " No , because I 'm not that clever writing in another part .
What I might do is split the girl 's part into two pieces . "
And so , Magenta and Columbia were split into two different people .
Who was Marianne going to play ? Why didn 't she play the one person ?
- I don 't know . Don 't ask . - Okay .
Because I think we had already said yes to Little Nell .
Then Marianne , I said , " So , I 've done it .
I 've worked it out where the two parts are split up into ...
I have the one part split into two . "
And , he went , " Oh , yeah , well , Marianne 's gone .
Marianne 's gone to India . "
I know . Was I ever so pleased she went on her trip .
And then it was you .
So , I think the two of you playing together like that
it is something symbiotic as if they 're like two little twins there .
Why do your veins stick out ?
Remember , people , when you 're hanging over the top of your loved one
the veins in your forehead stick out . Look at that , excuse me ?
- I didn 't look like that . - We don 't want that .
Look , Peter 's are there as well . Just bear it in mind .
That 's what we look like when we 're doing it .
- Yeah , when you 're on top . - Oh , God .
- That 's why we have our eyes closed . - I think , " Are the lights out ? "
Candlelight is very flattering , isn 't it ?
- Now , he actually whipped me here . - Yeah , he did .
- He caught me ... - That hurt !
He caught me several times .
But I didn 't complain , because I was a method actor .
A look of concern from young Barry there .
I thought he was cross-eyed .
Dear Barry , I met him at a convention in America and he said to me :
" Pat , you really thought I was Brad , didn 't you ? " And I said yes .
- Well , I did . - Did you ?
He was then . He 's actually great fun now .
He plays the mayor in something .
- He 's gray-haired and marvelous . - Spin City .
Something that is brilliant .
But he was so serious and he was in love with Susan .
And they were having a bad time , I think .
I think Barry 's got a good sense of humor .
He 's the only person that out of all of the kind of major players
that weren 't really connected with us ...
- ... in an organic sense . - That 's right .
That still maintains a sense of humor about the piece .
He turns up and he laughs about being Brad .
Brad gets called asshole on a regular basis and he puts up with it .
Barry is wonderful and he 's supported the show fantastically .
Every convention I 've met him at , I 've adored him .
But when he was doing this ... Maybe he was a method actor and became Brad .
I just thought he was wonderful .
I thought they were both such great players to come in
and join an already , kind of , happy unit that we were .
That must be very intimidating .
I love this . This was such a surprise to me .
Oh , yeah . On the wires .
You 'll see the carpet flip up in a moment as he comes around , somewhere .
That was terribly funny and I love us girls having ...
- That 's great . - ... you know ...
Actually , if you think about the mechanics , it 's pretty damn good .
It 's damn good .
This is the reason ! There was no way to get out of the lab .
They had no entrance into the laboratory .
- They had no door . - They realized , what do we do ?
- How do we get through this ? - Come through the wall !
- I know . They forgot to build a door . - They did .
That 's one of those brilliant things .
Oh , it 's wonderful . Doctor von Scott .
I wish he didn 't use a German accent . I would 've preferred an American one .
Really ? Right . Did you mind my German accent ?
No , you were fine .
But the von Scott one ... What I wanted ...
- Let 's use the German . - ... was a surprise .
But he says , " Or should I say , Doctor von Scott ? " ...
- ... with a German accent . - Couldn 't Jim or you have told him ?
I had
problems in certain areas ...
But he 's highly intelligent , Jonathan Adams .
He lives in a house that looks over a cemetery ...
- Called Tomb View . - Tomb View .
- Yes . - Very nice .
He 's a fine artist of fine art , if that makes sense .
- Of collages . - Was that a tautology ?
Tautology . Good word .
- Janet ! - Dr. Scott !
- Janet ! - Brad !
I don 't know whose idea it was to repeat this section but it works .
I 've got to tell you something amazing !
I 've forgotten his name . Alan Sharp ! Got it out .
He 's a script writer in Hollywood , comes from Scotland .
He 's a massive script writer .
There goes that gong ! And , when we get to it
when the statues are made , you know , of Little Nell .
He bought Little Nell and she was in his back garden in L.A.
- No . - Yes .
Alan Sharp bought Little Nell 's body .
Her statue .
With the plinths . I never understood the plinths .
I didn 't understand why we didn 't make them disappear .
I wish I 'd become a body .
Those are the most beautiful glass , lead-lighted doors .
I want to know where they are .
The first time I saw them I wanted them .
Can I just say why the table is laid like this ?
It 's because we 're Transylvanians . We didn 't know how to give a dinner .
This was Brian Thomson 's idea . We 've got all these peculiar spoons
and pee-pee bottles from the hospital and jam jars and whatever
because we didn 't know how to entertain . I rather love that idea .
I said , " Would you set this , would you serve the stuff ? "
I went , " I ain 't gonna , I don 't know how to do it .
So , I 'll throw it , I 'll dribble it and I don 't give a monkey 's what I do . "
Nobody had had a conversation about that .
- But it was quite anarchic , wasn 't it ? - Yes .
- If I you think about it . - Yes .
A toast .
To absent friends .
But he 's got his beer mug , you know . You see ?
- Yes , he 's got his stein . - Yes .
Happy birthday to you
Happy birthday , dear Rocky
- Happy birthday to you - Shall we ?
I think Peter Hinwood 's acting here , this simple acting , is wonderful .
- He broke my heart . - It 's naturalistic and lovely .
No ego involved in it , which is delightful .
She 's pretty sexy , that girl on the right there .
I could give her the one .
Show how she chews her food .
What happened to her ? Of course , you know , I didn 't ...
There are those beautiful doors to slam behind them . They 're gone .
- Gone ? - They were stolen .
They 're no longer in that hotel .
This was " Eddie 's Teddy . "
When we were doing the stage show
this song wasn 't in it and the show was so short , thank God
you were told to write another song . You came back with this the next day .
I thought , " We 've got to learn another song .
This is awful . "
And then when we sang it , we used to sing it ...
Then when they sang it in here they went ...
- That was a different ... - Different thing .
I think the film was better . Singing it on stage used to bore me to death .
That picked it up slightly .
Mr. Hartley again . The lovely Mr. Hartley .
This is Whistler 's Mother , of course , with Meat Loaf playing her .
Where are those doors today ...
Give over about them ! I 'll find you doors like that .
Somebody 's got them somewhere and they 're worth something .
All right . I 'll find your doors .
They were very special . That 's why they disappeared .
That 's why they disappeared .
There he is .
A low-down , cheap little punk .
- We didn 't know ... - It was very touching .
- ... what was under the table . - No , we didn 't .
- That wasn 't told to anybody . - I love this .
This , here , is the Baby Doll cot .
Her bed is from the film Baby Doll .
I love that touch .
So we didn 't know what was under the table .
It 's kind of fascinating , because the horror that goes around
the response is kind of real , isn 't it ?
All the reactions when we were eating at times
looked as if we knew that we were eating him .
- And I didn 't know . - No .
- Nobody knew . - No , nobody knew .
And then , Tim Curry knew he was going to have to pull off that thing .
Hoopla ! There 's another hoopla .
If you 're pulling that , you would shout hoopla , okay ?
He had to do that in one , otherwise you would reset the table .
And then , there was old Meat under the table .
Skeleton .
But we didn 't know .
And the reactions . Well , I know mine .
I was just amazed .
This film was like some other world unfolding to me .
It was like I was in the story that was happening .
That 's strange when you talk about that .
Because it was that surreal quality to the movie that was very disturbing .
We 'd been doing the show for months before we made the movie .
Yes .
It ran for 1 : 35 when it was slow , 1 : 30 when it was on time
and 1 : 25 when it was really hiking along .
Yep .
And when we went to watch the movie , which was 90 minutes exactly
and it seemed so long
and slow and so gently unfolding .
You go , " How can that happen ? "
We 've got more dialogue in the movie . We 've got extra things in the movie .
How can we actually add these longueurs
and yet still be running at an hour 30 ?
- I don 't understand it . - I see .
There was a surreal , dreamlike quality
a very dreamlike quality to Rocky Horror , the movie
which was never present in Rocky Horror , the stage show .
No , because I 'd done the stage show again 21 years later
which goes so fast you think you 're going to die from it .
So yes , it is extraordinary .
What are we saying ? The movie 's the same length .
It 's exactly a 90-minute movie . That 's what Jim wanted to make .
Good God . And it 's so visual .
We 've got added dialogue , added scenes
and the things always pad out when you 're making the movie .
Things on stage have to be much more succinct .
Oh , right . So we 've hit a point .
It seemed so much slower .
It added a dreamlike quality to it .
Which I think you were talking about earlier on .
So we 're back in the pink room now .
- In the lab . - In the lab with no door .
No in or out .
It would 've been shot before that dinner sequence , wouldn 't it ?
And we 're gonna see them put through the transducer .
They 're gonna send us to the planet ? Planet Schmanet Janet ?
Yes . And they all had to do ...
What I wanted to see happen here
was kind of a ray of light come around them
and have them dissolve and disappear .
That 's the way I wanted it . So their bodies were in a state of flux .
I see .
That 's what I wanted .
When that reference was made , somewhere between an entrance and exit .
- They decided to put them into ... - Madame Tussaud .
... in these strange kind of plaster casts .
They had to find a position which ... They had to get molded in it first .
- It 's happened to me . - A day of agony .
I 've done that myself in the play .
- They had to do that position . - It 's quite nice .
It 's very nice , but they 're on a plinth .
Why are they on a plinth ?
They 've got to find this position that they 're gonna end up in .
It 's fine there .
But she 's on a plinth . Where 'd that plinth come from ?
- That little base . Where is it from ? - Because they had to make it stand .
Yes , because the statue had to stand .
- Did the transducer make a base too ? - Oh , I see .
- I just think it 's a bit tacky . - A wee bit tacky , that .
A wee bit tacky .
I love this bit . Nellie and I practiced in the cold caravan .
She said , " How am I gonna play this scene ? "
She never knew if her nipple would go through that rip .
- Yes , she did ! - Did she ?
Oh , yes , she did .
She was always a flasher , that girl .
And my girlfriend 's written some books on that .
That 's an interesting case .
Oh , which girlfriend 's that ?
Dr. Estela Welldon .
She deals with female flashers .
Sorry .
What 's the name of this book ? And the publisher ?
Mother , Madonna , Whore .
- Is it still in print ? - Yep .
- At popular prices ? - Yes !
It 'll teach you a thing or two .
Rather nice , that outfit Tim 's wearing .
- Beautiful . - That 's rather nice .
The little top 's rather nice .
I 'd get one of those myself , actually . I 'm getting a bit , you know ?
No , no . Shut up . I don 't care about your clothes .
Can we look at this ? This is the slowest burn you 've ever seen , okay ?
That is the longest take of a look that killed Tim Curry .
- Yeah . - It killed him .
I 'm sorry .
And your breasts were rather arresting .
- I was never interested in those . - No , but we were as viewers .
Oh , Lord , I never thought of that .
- Did you not ? - No .
- Oh , my God . - I felt totally dressed .
You thought it was your acting that got the attention ?
Yes !
You poor , sad little fool .
That was the slowest burn . You could count that one .
Lillian Gish couldn 't have done that .
That 's our elbow copulating , so the fans think .
Elbow connection .
Elbow creek .
There 's a Pearl , opposed to Jacobs .
Could you fill me in on Jacob 's Creek ?
It 's wine from Australia .
Oh , is this Freudian ? It 's not a little bit like Barrassa Pearl .
It 's bloody nice , that Barrassa Pearl .
Queen Adelaide , that 's pretty good too .
There 's old Charlie .
Darling Charlie .
Charlie . He 's fabulous , Charlie .
I met a friend of his , a colleague of his ...
I wouldn 't have thought he had one .
Oh , yes . He did .
- Apart from Ava ? - Ava .
Whom I adored .
I became a movie star because of Ava Gardner .
I don 't mean a movie star , an actress .
Actor , I think , if you 're gonna be P.C.
No , no , no .
I am very ashamed of any actress who calls herself an actor .
- Why ? - Dorothy Parker said :
" Scratch an actor and you 'll find an actress underneath . "
Well , it certainly worked in my case , but how about you ?
I 'm very proud to be an actress . I 'd never wish to be an actor .
- But pride comes before the fall , Pat . - No , no , no .
Actors are such different creatures to actresses .
- Are they ? - Yes , totally .
I thought this goo , the gunk that Tim put on his face was a good move .
It was so brilliant , and I didn 't know what it was about .
I saw him and thought , " What 's he doing ? "
He was getting ready for the floor show .
You 've met those people that do that kind of stuff ?
Well , one does . Sorry ?
That was a brilliant idea . I don 't know whose it was .
When he came out looking like that , I didn 't know why .
But then ... You think I 'm slow , don 't you ?
No , would I ?
I think this floor show 's wonderful , and Sue Blane 's costumes , stunning .
I mean , this is before Michael Jackson , you know ?
Look at the sleeves on these things .
The one with the feather .
It 's extraordinary , what she was thinking of .
And I have to say , I 've met lawyers , I 've met everyone
I 've been on trains , I 've been everywhere and they 've all done it .
Exactly .
They 've all fishnet .
But will they get us off next time we 're up before the big ?
I doubt it very much .
I have to say , on the night in question I was wearing fishnets .
- And I had an orange in my mouth . - Yes .
No , but seriously , I can 't tell you the people I 've met .
They talk to me , and if it 's ever mentioned they say they 've done it .
Strange . What did you do , Richard ?
I 've released people from their kind of
male / female polarized parameters .
But English males have been involved in that .
It 's very frightening for the Brad character lost in no-man 's-land
because as a result of the changes .
Here , Janet , you see
this is where the worm has turned and everything 's changed around .
She gets her kind of strength and her power .
The hunter-gatherer male gets lost because she 's now got her power .
I see . So that 's what 's happened today , actually .
Truthfully , yeah. it does mirror today 's society
and I think that 's one reason why the show has some longevity .
Good Lord .
- This tower behind us ? - Yeah .
We 'll see Frank and Rocky , after their death , climb up that .
But of course it 's gonna be stunt doubles .
And they came along , and the guy that was playing the Frank part
had no idea that he had to dress up like Tim .
Oh , Lord !
And it was a wonderful moment , a wonderful day ...
Oh , no !
- ... where the guy looked at the stunt ... - The stuntman !
... and then went , " I 'll go and get ready now . "
And then had to dress like that .
And he was extra butch because he didn 't want anyone to think ...
- That he was like that . - Yeah .
And the more butch he got , the campier it all became .
That was a fab moment in time .
I 'd like to go back . If I had a time machine , I 'd like to spend
half an hour there watching that .
Just for that joy .
And here we are , talking about the RKO tower here .
Originally , of course , we wanted the Twentieth Century Fox tower .
- Why didn 't we ? - Fox wouldn 't allow us to do it .
Though it was a Fox movie , they wouldn 't allow us to do it .
And the head of Fox now will probably say :
" You know , what 's going on here ? "
Decisions were made , and it was camp , you know ?
Excuse me , this was really risqué .
Even in Los Angeles today , gay men are not allowed to
expose themselves too much , you know ?
We 're very lucky .
Actually , it 's the British gays in Los Angeles today , isn 't it ?
Ian McKellen ...
Madonna 's chum .
- Rupert ... - Rupert , yes .
... Everett .
It 's a British-driven kind of acceptance .
- Yes . - An opening up , you know ?
Yeah , but the British have always been very free about that .
Nice , that little touch of the Leonardo
touch of God on the bottom of the swimming pool .
And it was " A million-dollar shot " as Lou said
when those clouds disappear and the smoke disappears
and we come down on the overhead shot of Tim .
That was the million-dollar shot .
They go in of course . In they go to the water and they have to come out .
Did Jim Sharman , our director , cut when they go back into the song again ?
- No , he didn 't . They come out ... - Gasping !
- And they had to dance . - See ?
Susan was very sick . You don 't want to have that conversation ...
No , I will have it .
... about her illness here at the time .
- But she was very , very sick now . - Yeah .
Here she is , thrown once again into water on a cold winter 's evening
to come out of this water into the cold studio .
And sing and dance and ...
- I know it was hard , but by God ... - And it was slippery .
I know , and it 's all been hard , but it 's been worth it .
And it 's given so much pleasure to so many people .
You 're allowed to die .
You 're allowed to die . You must die for one 's art .
My husband died playing King Lear .
Four hours , 20 minutes . He went through the pissing rain on the heath
and he was a dying man . So I 'm sorry .
There you go .
And King Lear died playing your husband ?
That 's quite interesting .
Here they come out of the water here .
There 's a cut there . You would 've thought that was a tight moment
to allow them . But no .
They could have emptied the pool .
But they 'd come out of the water and they 're still wet there .
They were slipping everywhere .
But what 's the point ? Maybe no time .
There was no time , but they were trying to hang on
to some semblance of dance , some semblance of movement .
Some semblance of choreography .
And if you were dying from ill health , as well , you know ?
- But they 're doing it ! - Yes , they are .
They 're called troupers . Troupers !
They 're there .
And here we are .
- This is our moment . - Ha , ha .
- With my Ramon Gow hairdo . - It was a brilliant idea .
It was my idea to put in the head .
That was your idea . You had to match my bloody hairdo !
I have a coat hanger in the top of my head .
But look what I 've got , you know ?
It had to go somewhere . We 'd just stand for hours .
What was that smoke ? Oil , wasn 't it ?
Oh , yeah .
- It was killing , that was . - Yeah .
- Oh , she 's off . - Yes , you 're leaving .
I 'm pressing a button .
- Are you ? - The sonic beam .
I 'll never forgive you , because as you go down with that gun
you 'll see you put it in my face .
Oh , no . I didn 't , did I ?
How dreadful ! I had no idea .
Oh , yeah .
It 's funny this day because we have the extras that bleed in .
These are people that never turned up , just for the day for this shot .
They bleed in and out , because it 's Frank 's fantasy , isn 't it ?
There was a new idea , and it 's brilliant .
They got the gig because they owned the evening dress .
And I must admit to this , I knew a few because I had been an extra .
- Oh , no ! - Yes .
I can 't believe that !
I knew them , because I had done extra work with them .
Oh , dear .
You 've got to start somewhere .
They bring their scrapbooks along , don 't they ?
- I didn 't know about that . - Oh , they do . And they say :
I wasn 't a serious extra .
" Would you come over here , Richard ? You 'll love this .
Look at this , look at this . "
They bring in scrapbooks and they 've got photos of them on different gigs .
Oh , look , look at this ! Now I hated this
because Jim Sharman said to me , " Yawn at that moment . "
He said , " Yawn , yawn . " I thought he was being so brilliant .
No , he was talking to Jan , that guy from Norway behind you .
No , no , no .
" Jan , Jan. "
He said , " Yawn at him . " I thought , " I 'm so ashamed , I can 't . "
I wouldn 't yawn at any actor or anyone doing anything .
It 's so rude . And Tim was being so brilliant .
This song , it broke my heart .
Judy Garland . That 's a Judy Garland shot .
Cards for sorrow , cards for pain .
Jim said , " Yawn . " I thought , " No , I can 't . I really hate to do that . "
It 's such a rude thing to do to any actor on the stage
because it 's sort of rather like you 're bored , you know ?
And I mean , not in acting , but within a performance too .
So I was very ashamed of doing that .
I wrote this song in about
1971 , I think . I was living in Fulham .
A nice thing about writing Rocky was I had a lot of songs in the drawer
and this was one of them .
It meant nothing . I used to bore the arse off people singing my songs .
You still do . No , you don 't ! You don 't !
And they used to go home going , " Oh , yeah , yeah , yeah . "
When this happened , they said :
" Oh , yes , I was there . I heard that song in the early days . "
It 's strange how things change , isn 't it ?
- Don 't be bitter , dear . - I 'm not at all bitter .
- One mustn 't be . - Sweet as ...
- Look at the feathers in his hair . - ... lemon .
And they disappear and they fade in his dreams .
How sentimental .
The deck chairs are a great idea .
Nice thought .
Yep . End of the pier .
And of course we have this ray gun
which again , equals the American Gothic pitchfork at the beginning .
Which you threw
at the side . You threw it down .
Pitched away .
I didn 't get that , I 'm terribly sorry . I 've been around for how long ?
I have that pitchfork . It doesn 't have that thing
off the top of it , that little peak .
But I have the handle and the rest of it .
The amazing tie-up for Mr. Thomson is extraordinary , isn 't it ?
I mean , in the work and the ideas .
Yeah . It 's almost a noose .
I beg your pardon ?
It 's almost what ?
What ? You said , " tie-up . "
- A noose . Oh , a noose ! I love it . - It was a knotty ...
- A knotty conundrum . - I thought you were being Greek .
Yes , quite Greek .
The twitch in the eyes . They have that .
- The gun ... - Nellie dead .
You got pretty nasty , kid .
This is very primitive overlay of special effects here .
That , for instance .
Today , again , we could do that with computers so easily .
And they made poor old Tim climb
those ropes . He shouldn 't have done that .
No . Insurance-wise .
I remember experienced men saying , " This shouldn 't be happening .
He shouldn 't be doing that . No , no , no .
Not your principal actor , he shouldn 't be doing that . "
I bet he had a great time doing it , though . He was into it by then .
There are the real performers there .
It really is very primitive , isn 't it ? The special effects .
- It adds something to it . - It 's divine .
- I love it . - It does add something to it .
Then of course this is Fay Wray , isn 't it ?
It 's King Kong ?
That 's King Kong and that 's why I love it 's RKO .
The stunt double .
RKO made King Kong , didn 't they ?
Did they ?
RKO made a lot of science fiction movies
the whole studio went through a huge change .
I love this . I was given these new lines .
I love it !
My most beloved sister should 've tipped it for you
with that relationship between the two of us , but still it didn 't .
I was so late , and you 're such a sulky git , you know .
- They never liked me ! - No , they didn 't .
It was wonderful .
And to think I had a coat hanger in my head there .
It worked .
It did .
I looked like a question mark , the human question mark .
But our underwear looks nice .
What 's that extra little band around the top of your leg ?
- I can 't work that one out . - It 's more interesting than yours .
I can see the top of your stocking there .
But what 's the one in the middle ? What 's that ?
- What 's that all about ? - I think it 's ... I don 't know .
How can I remember who dressed me ?
You dressed yourself , obviously .
With no bloody dressers ?
Oh , my darling sister .
What is that extra bit between your knickers and your stockings ?
I have no idea .
Oh , I don 't know .
But it 's all for you , my darling , and the stars .
Something up there anyway in the Milky Way .
Stop it .
Look , I can see them . I can feel the stars shining down on us .
And what about this ?
Excuse me , are we talking about camp acting here or not ? Great stuff .
- There 's nothing camp about me . - It 's brilliant . It is brilliant .
We should 've got Oscars for that , mate .
- This was nice , the cut-backs to the ... - I love that .
- I saw several endings . Have you ? - No .
I have . And it doesn 't necessarily go back to that .
This is interesting . We couldn 't afford a special effects shot
so when this goes up you will see the same house behind .
- You see the house behind ? - No .
Through there ?
And this was cut from a lot of the original versions .
This song was cut .
We cut straight to the rated verse .
We cut Brad and Janet 's verses of this song
and went straight to the narrator 's verse on the original movie .
- And it made no sense whatsoever . - I see .
But we needed this .
There was a very long intro that Richard Hartley devised for this song .
I suggested they cut straight to Brad 's verse .
They cut straight to narrator 's verse
which cut both Brad and Janet 's verse , which was rather stupid
because it was kind of nice to have these two verses .
They make the whole thing tie up , the whole song tie up .
- And they went round and round . - So had you much control over this ?
No , not really . But I had my five pennies ' worth .
Okay .
I was allowed to have a voice
but was no longer , you know , no more important than anybody else 's .
This was interesting , this went into an overhead shot
and the spin shot , which was the same overhead shot , probably
exactly the same place we did the overhead shot
of Tim in the pool .
And that spin that turns into the globe
which is Mr. Sharman again .
I wrote this song in
1970 , or ' 71 .
I was in Nottingham , I was doing Hair .
We were on tour with the show and I wrote this song and I had no idea ...
I had been to see , I remember I went to see Arturo Ui .
I was meant to be in that with Simon Keller .
On we go .
Leonard Rossiter .
I went to see Leonard Rossiter
on a wet Wednesday afternoon at the Saville Theatre .
And it was about a 100 people in a theater designed to take 2000 people .
And he played it as if it was first night , opening night ...
How divine .
... and showed us the way that it works and the way you are here today
I will perform for you .
And he did the last segment of that show , that closing speech ...
so beautifully and so brilliantly
that I wrote that song off that speech .
" You gotta watch out for fascism , because the bitch is living still . "
And that entire song was written off that premise
written off that speech .
It 's been a charming little sit-down here , watching this movie .
Lots of these players are no longer with us
and lots of them will go on to do bigger and greater things .
It was a charming moment in time , wasn 't it , to have been part of that ?
It 's been one of the greatest
the best things I 've ever done . And I 've done lots of things .
But for me , this is the most glorious thing I 've ever done .
To me , it 's been the most uplifting ...
Of course it gave me the name Pat Quinn that has buried me
because I 'm associated with Rocky Horror forever .
So people don 't take it very seriously because of that .
However , I would never not have done it .
It 's just been a total delight for me .
I 've loved being in Rocky Horror .
I think it 's time to take our clothes off and have a bit of rock and roll now .
Okay .
English - US - Commentary